All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is ט"ז
Tes Zayin and we pick up in the middle of ט"ו עמוד
ב', Tes Vav Amud Bet, הארי והזאב. Ha'ari vehaze'ev. So we're dealing
now with the case of a שור הנסקל shor haniskal gets a
בית דין Beis Din of 23 and this leads the משנה Mishnah
to discuss something it discusses in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, which is
that if you have these wild animals,
so the first opinion said, fine, normal הלכה halacha you need a
בית דין Beis Din of 23 but they can become a שור
הנסקל. shor haniskal. But the next opinion in the משנה Mishnah said,
what did it say? It said רבי אליעזר אומר כל הקודם זכה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer kol hakodem zachah. רבי עקיבא אומר מיתתן בבית דין
של שלושה. Rabbi Akiva omer misasan be-Beis Din shel sheloshah. So Rabbi
Eliezer says
you don't wait for a בית דין. Beis Din. These things are
dangerous animals. The
שור הנסקל shor haniskal was an ox that once gored three times.
It's not a lion. It's not an animal that's completely, fundamentally, majorly
dangerous and therefore these animals just kill them. Don't wait for a
בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, so אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, והוא שהמיתו. vehu shehemitu. That's only
if they actually killed somebody. It's not that every time somebody has
a pet lion or a pet bear, go ahead and kill it.
It's only if they've actually demonstrated that they're dangerous. Then don't wait
for a בית דין. Beis Din. אבל לא המיתו, Aval lo hemitu,
if they haven't killed, לא, lo, you don't. אלמא קסבר יש להם
תרבות ויש להם בעלים. Al-ma kasavar yesh lahem tarbus veyesh lahem be'alim.
So he holds that these can be domesticated. It is possible. It's
really hard, okay, but it's possible to keep them as pets and
therefore יש להם בעלים, yesh lahem be'alim, you can have them owners
and therefore until they've demonstrated that they're going back to their fundamentally
wild nature, then you do not have a right to kill them.
But once they do, then you're afraid that they're much more dangerous
than a שור הנסקל shor haniskal and just go ahead and kill
them without a בית דין. Beis Din. רבי יוחנן אמר אף על
פי שלא המיתו, Rabbi Yochanan amar af al pi she-lo hemitu, even
if they have not yet killed anybody. Exactly. You can go kill
my pet lion and you can't demand reimbursement. Exactly. אלמא קסבר אין
להם תרבות ואין להם בעלים. Al-ma kasavar ein lahem tarbus ve-ein lahem
be'alim. They can't be domesticated and nobody is a real owner of
them. These are at their core they're wild animals and therefore just
save, help society and kill them wherever you see them. Okay, תנן,
Tnan, רבי אליעזר אומר כל הקודם להרגן זכה. Rabbi Eliezer omer kol
hakodem lehorgam zachah. משנה Mishnah says that Rabbi Eliezer says the one
who kills them first merits. So what does it mean merits? בשלמא
לרבי יוחנן למאי זכה
זכה לעורן. Bi-shlama le-Rabbi Yochanan le-mai zachah, zachah le-oran. Since nobody can
really own them, so you merit that if you killed them then
you get to keep their עור, or, their skin, which is something
that we teach elsewhere that the person who kills them gets to
keep their skin. Tan the lion, keep its skin. Exactly. You see
I have a pet lion, you go ahead and kill it and
you keep the skin. אלא, Ella, that's a good incentive for you
to do it. אלא לריש לקיש למאי זכה? Ella le-Reish Lakish, le-mai
zachah? Since Reish Lakish says they do have owners, then even if
somebody were to kill it, then the owner would get to keep
their skin. So how did that guy merit?
כיון שהמיתו, kevan shehemitu, not just because they have owners, excuse me,
it's not just that, it's also the logic that since he requires
that they go ahead and kill and have murdered before they could
be killed or that they whatever killed before they can be killed,
so כיון שהמיתו, kevan shehemitu, since we're requiring that you're not allowed
to kill them unless they themselves have already taken a life, so
that means that conceptually שוינהו רבנן כמאן דגמר דינייהו ואסירי בהנאה נינהו.
shavininhu rabanan keman degamar dinayhu ve-assiru be-hana'ah ninhu. So it means that
we're still working within the model of a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal.
It's a very interesting point, right? It's like we're saying if you
say kill them before they've done anything then it's just get rid
of them, they're a hazard. But if you have to wait till
they kill, what we're saying is they're a שור הנסקל shor haniskal
but a שור הנסקל shor haniskal that we're not going to wait
for a court case, a שור הנסקל shor haniskal we're just going
to expedite the whole process. But if we're fundamentally working with the
model of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, then there you can't derive
benefit. So מאי זכה? mai zachah? What זכות zechus do you have?
You can't get the עור. or. זכה לשמיא. Zachah lishmaya. Oh, you
get the merit of doing the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, תניא כותיה דריש
לקיש, Tanya kavasiah de-Reish Lakish, we taught like Reish Lakish. אחד שור
שהמית ואחד בהמה וחיה שהמיתו בעשרים ושלושה. Echad shor shehemit ve-echad behemah
vechayah shehemitu be-esrim ushloshah. רבי אליעזר אומר שור שהמית בעשרים ושלושה ושאר
בהמה וחיה, Rabbi Eliezer omer shor shehemit be-esrim ushloshah veshear behemah vechayah,
not just limited now to a lion and a bear and whatever,
anything that is not an ox, any other בהמה, behemah, like what,
like a dog? I mean, it's crazy. This is a much more
expansive read than we said before, right? If it's not an ox,
any other animal I think is way too wild once it's killed.
But this is why it's Reish Lakish because it says שהמיתו, shehemitu,
that they actually killed. Okay, שהמיתו, shehemitu, כל הקודם להרגן זכה בהן
לשמיא. kol hakodem lehorgam zachah bahen lishmaya. And that's the זכה לשמיא,
zachah lishmaya, you don't get to keep the skin. So it's Reish
Lakish but it also really expands the category. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi
Akiva omer, now Rabbi Akiva says no, no, no, they need a
בית דין Beis Din of 23. גמרא Gemara says היינו תנא קמא?
haynu tana kamma? That's what the תנא קמא Tana Kamma said, that
they need a בית דין Beis Din of 23. No, איכא בינייהו
נחש. ikka beineihu nachash. The תנא קמא Tana Kamma would say that
even by a snake you would need a בית דין Beis Din
of 23 and based on other משניות mishnayos in בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva might concede that by a snake that's
particularly dangerous and that does not need a בית דין. Beis Din.
Okay, אין דנין. Ein danin. Now we get to the
fact that or just just that. Now we get to the fact
that a שבט shevet needs a בית דין Beis Din of 71.
So האי שבט דחטא במאי? hai shevet dechata be-mai? What was the
sin of this שבט? shevet? אילימא שחילל
את השבת, Ileima she-chilel es ha-Shabbos, a normal sin. So אימר דפליג
רחמנא בין יחיד למרובים לענין עבודה זרה. emar depalig rachmana bein yachid
le-merubim le-inyan avodah zarah. So what makes you treat it as a
tribe? Like why do you treat it like the whole tribe is
coming to court? It's just all many, many, many, many citizens, right?
But it's all individuals. There's no, they're not treated as a corporate
entity for the individuals' חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. Okay, the only time
the גמרא Gemara looked at it as a community was by עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. בשאר מצוות מי פלגי? be'sha'ar mitzvos mi palgi? It
doesn't look at it this way by other מצוות. mitzvos. אלא בשבט
שהודח. ela be'shevet she'huda'ach. Fine,
the whole tribe committed עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, so it's like a
big עיר הנדחת. Ir Hanidachas. So למימרא דבדינא דרבים דיינינן ליה? lemaimra
de'bedina de'rabim dayanina lei?
Now so in certain ways anyway that's obvious because an עיר הנדחת
Ir Hanidachas is seventy-one. So if a whole שבט shevet is an
עיר הנדחת, Ir Hanidachas, of course it's seventy-one, which is how some
read the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. But the בבלי Bavli has even another question,
which is not only is it obvious, it's actually wrong. If the
city gets too big, it stops being an עיר הנדחת. Ir Hanidachas.
It's an ironic הלכה. halacha. Okay, it says למימרא דבדינא דרבים דיינינן
ליה, lemaimra de'bedina de'rabim dayaninan lei, are you saying we would treat
a whole שבט shevet as like a as like the masses that
committed עבודה זרה Avoda Zara like an עיר הנדחת? Ir Hanidachas? כמאן?
keman? Who is that going like? לא כרבי יאשיה ולא כרבי יונתן.
lo k'Rabbi Yoshiya ve'lo k'Rabbi Yonasan. It's not going like either of
these תנאים. Tanna'im. דתניא ותנו ברייתא: de'tanya ve'tanu baraisa: עד כמה עושים
עיר הנדחת? ad kamah osin Ir Hanidachas? How big does a city
have to be to be an עיר הנדחת? Ir Hanidachas? מי' ועד
עשרה דברי רבי יאשיה. mi'yud ve'ad asarah divrei Rabbi Yoshiya.
Rabbi Yoshiya's got a pretty small city. Okay, עיר ir is like
a town, between ten and a hundred. Okay, more than a hundred
you're not—I said עשרה—מי' ועד קוף מי' ועד מאה, from ten to
a hundred, דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. More than that you're
no longer a city, I don't know what you are, you're a
metropolis. Okay, רבי יונתן—תוספות actually says that the size of ten and
a hundred are in in a פסוק pasuk in what do you
call it, in עמוס. Amos. Okay, רבי יונתן אומר מקוף ועד רובו
מקוף ועד רובו, Rabbi Yonasan omer mi'kof ad rubo mi'kof ad rubo,
from a hundred until the majority of a שבט shevet של שבט,
shel shevet, that's a city. Okay, but once it's the majority of
a שבט shevet
then they don't
do the less than a hundred then it's just like יחידים. yechidim.
Then it's just יחידים yechidim that worshipped עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. And
even רבי
יונתן—exactly,
Rabbi Yonasan
and you don't whatever destroy the city, it's just like individuals. ואפילו
רבי יונתן לא קאמר אלא רובו ve'afillu Rabbi Yonasan lo q'amar ela
rubo aval kulo... until the majority. Now you could say רובו ככולו,
rubo ke'kulo, but no, if it's literally the whole שבט, shevet, לא
אמר. lo amar. That would no longer be an עיר הנדחת Ir
Hanidachas and ironically it would go back to the rule of individuals,
which would be quite ironic. So anyway the גמרא Gemara says that
would be obvious and also it wouldn't be true. אמר רב מתנה
הכא, amar Rav Masnah hacha, so what's the idea of שבט? shevet?
הכא בנשיא שבט שחטא עסקינן, hacha be'nasi shevet she'chata askinan, we're dealing
with the head of a שבט. shevet. Top of דף טז עמוד
א. daf tes zayin amud alef. Okay, מי לא אמר רבי אדא
בר אהבה כל הדבר הגדול יביאו אליך? mi lo amar Rabbi Adda
bar Ahava kol hadavar hagadol yavi'u eilecha? How do we know the
idea that a כהן גדול kohen gadol and a מלך melech are
judged by seventy-one? Because יתרו Yisro says to משה Moshe every big
matter they should bring to you, יביאו אליך, yavi'u eilecha, דבריו של
גדול, devarav shel gadol, matters that deal with major figures. Okay, so
האי נמי גדול הוא, hai nami gadol hu, so similarly the head
of a שבט, shevet, that comes to a בית דין beis din
of seventy-one. משה Moshe represents the whole בית דין, beis din, the
whole סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, seventy-one. So that's what it means, the head of
a שבט. shevet. For a capital crime?
עבודה זרה? Avoda Zara?
Well, we're going to see about that. We're going to see what
type of crime. Certainly not limited to עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, certainly
any capital crime. But we're going to see in a minute maybe
every everything they're accused of, we'll see about that.
Okay, עולא אמר רבי אלעזר בבואי על עסקי נחלות וכחטילתה של ארץ
ישראל. Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar bivnai al iskei nachalos uketchilasa shel Eretz
Yisrael. No, when שבטים shevatim are debating who has which property like
the boundary lines and then like I when we did it in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi I said like maybe it's any dispute among שבטים
shevatim you need some court that sits above the שבטים. shevatim. But
this is making it specifically when it's about arguing about the boundaries.
Okay, and just like the original division of the land of Israel
was with a בית דין beis din of seventy-one. מה תחלתה שבעים
ואחד אף כאן שבעים ואחד. mah techilasah shivim ve'echad af kan shivim
ve'echad. So and we're going to learn that later that the שבט
shevet originally the land was divided was with a בית דין beis
din of seventy-one. אם תחלתה קלפי ואורים ותומים וכל ישראל... im techilasah
kalfi ve'urim vetumim vechol Yisrael... wait, let's make it exactly like they
originally did it. They had a קלפי kalfi draw lots and they
had the אורים ותומים urim vetumim and it was in the presence
of all of the people of Israel. So let's say anytime there's
a dispute among שבטים shevatim we have to recreate that whole setting.
Obviously that's absurd. אף כאן קלפי ואורים ותומים וכל ישראל? af kan
kalfi ve'urim vetumim vechol Yisrael? אלא מחוור כרב מתנה. ela machvar ke'Rav
Masnah. So they reject that. It's better like רב מתנה. Rav Masnah.
To me it's a very reasonable thing, meaning don't emphasize like the
original division, just say if there's a dispute amongst שבטים shevatim you
need a בית דין beis din of seventy-one, who else is going
to hear it? Anyway רבינא אמר Ravina amar third answer, לעולם בשבט
שהודח. le'olam be'shevet she'huda'ach. We're dealing with a שבט shevet that committed
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. ודקשיא לך בדינא דרבים דיינינן ליה, ve'de'kashya lach
bedina de'rabim dayaninan lei, you said what, we're going to judge them
as masses, they're not an עיר הנדחת Ir Hanidachas if it's a
whole שבט. shevet. אין, in, yes, we're going to judge them as
a corporate entity. אף על גב דקטלינן ביחיד, af al gav de'katlinan
beyachid, even though the actual execution is like individuals, we don't you
know wipe out the whole city and all those types of things.
Nevertheless, what type of a court hears the case? בדינא דרבים דיינינן
ליה. bedina de'rabim dayaninan lei. You're still going to have a בית
דין beis din the same type of בית דין beis din that
would deal with a whole city. Okay, it might be the judgment
is the same judgment you would mete out to individuals, but the
court is a court of seventy-one when you're dealing with the sin
of a whole שבט. shevet. מי לא אמר רבי חמא ברבי יוסי
אמר רבי אושעיא? mi lo amar Rabbi Chama bar bi Yosei amar
Rabbi Oshaya? Because how do you know the idea that an עיר
הנדחת Ir Hanidachas has a בית דין beis din of seventy-one? We
learn it from the following. When it speaks about worshipping עבודה avodah.
זרה *avoda zara*, והוצאת את האיש ההוא או את האשה ההיא אל
שעריך she'arecha, *vehotzeisa es ha'ish hahu oh es ha'ishah hahi el she'arecha*.
שעריך *she'arecha* is the gates of your cities. So means the בית
דין Beis Din *beis din* of your cities. איש ואשה אתה מוציא
לשעריך *ish ve'ishah ata motzi lish'arecha*. When you're dealing with individuals, they're
judged by the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* of the city.
ואי אתה מוציא כל העיר כולה לשעריך *ve'i ata motzi kol ha'ir
kulo lish'arecha*. If the whole city has, you know, has sinned, that's
not judged by the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* of the
city, that's judged by the בית דין Beis Din, *beis din* of
seventy-one, the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* of כל ישראל Yisrael?
*Klal Yisrael*. So הכא נמי *hacha nami* here too, even though it's
not technically an עיר הנדחת *ir nidachas*, איש ואשה אתה מוציא לשעריך
ואי אתה מוציא כל שבט כולו לשעריך *ish ve'ishah ata motzi lish'arecha
ve'i ata motzi kol shevet kulo lish'arecha*. If the whole שבט *shevet*
has sinned, it requires a different בית דין Beis Din, *beis din*,
even though they're going to be judged as individuals. Of course once
you say that, it doesn't have to be עבודה זרה *avoda zara*.
Let the whole שבט *shevet* have worshiped, have been מחלל שבת *mechallel
Shabbos*, right? Because, you know, what you're sort of saying is if
it's so many then it's even though they're not a corporate entity
in terms of the judgment, as judgment they're being judged as individuals,
because it's such a big part of the population, it's judged by
a בית דין Beis Din, *beis din* of seventy-one, still not clear
why with that we're limiting it to the idea of עבודה זרה
*avoda zara*. Okay, so that's the idea of שבט *shevet*. ונביא שקר
*ve'navi sheker*, now false prophet. מנא הני מילי Mina hani mili, *mina
hani milli*? This all look familiar. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא אתיא
הזדה הזדה מזקן ממרא *ammar Rabbi Yosei berabbi Chanina asya hazada hazada
mi'zakein mamre*. מה להלן בשבעים ואחד אף כאן בשבעים ואחד *mah lehallan
beshivim ve'echad af kan beshivim ve'echad*. So the same way it says
אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי *asher yazid ledaber davar bishmi*, and by
the זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* it says, what does it say? ואשר
יזיד *va'asher yazid*, Michael what's the ואשר יזיד *va'asher yazid* by the
זקן ממרא *zakein mamre*? והאיש אשר יעשה בזדון *veha'ish asher ya'aseh bezadon*.
Thank you. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, now
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi. *Yerushalmi* ends it there, but the בבלי Bavli *Bavli*
has a question. והזדה כי כתיבא בקטלה הוא hu, דכתיבא *ve'hazada ki
kesiva be'ktala hu dekesiva*. וקטלה בעשרים ושלשה *u'ktala be'esrim u'shlosha*. So here
the בבלי *Bavli* asks an important question. Guess what, you never would
have thought this. א זקן ממרא *a zakein mamre* has to rebel
against the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* of seventy-one, but he's
judged and has his court case in a בית דין Beis Din
*beis din* of twenty-three. Does not actually need the בית דין Beis
Din *beis din* of seventy-one. Because the
פסוק pasuk
*posuk* is אשר יעשה בזדון *asher ya'aseh bezadon*, right, is that he
is, that פסוק pasuk, *posuk* אשר יעשה בזדון *asher ya'aseh bezadon* is
when he is rebelling against the בית דין beis din *beis din*
of seventy-one, but there's nowhere in this משנה *mishna* does it say
that a זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* is judged with a בית דין
beis din, *beis din* of seventy-one. It's very ironic, but a זקן
ממרא *zakein mamre* is judged with a בית דין beis din, *beis
din* of twenty-three. So it says you can't make this גזירה שוה
*gezeira shava*. והזדה כי כתיבא בקטלה הוא דכתיבא *ve'hazada ki kesiva be'ktala
hu dekesiva*. When it says by the זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* where
it says, you know, והאיש אשר יעשה בזדון לבלתי שמוע אל הכהן
אשר יהיה שם לשרת את ה' אלקיך או אל השופט ומת האיש
ההוא ובערת הרע מקרבך *veha'ish asher ya'aseh bezadon levilti shmoa el hakohein
asher yiheyeh sham lishareis es Hashem Elokecha oh el hashofet umas ha'ish
hahu uvi'arta hara mikirbecha*.
So that פסוק pasuk. *posuk* of זדון *zadon* by the זקן ממרא
*zakein mamre* is where he's being executed. וקטלה בעשרים ושלשה *v'ktala be'esrim
u'shlosha*, and ironically, the execution of a זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* is
twenty-three. So you can't learn it by the פסוק pasuk. *posuk* of
זדון *zadon*, because that would get you twenty-three. אלא Ela אמר ריש
לקיש גמר דבר דבר *ella ammar Reish Lakish gamar davar davar*, which
is the other דרשה drasha *drasha* we saw in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi,
*Yerushalmi*. מהמרדתו *me'hamradato*, from his rebellion, right? It says by because by
the זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* it says, what's the פסוק pasuk *posuk*
by the דבר *davar*? ועשית על פי הדבר אשר יגידו לך *ve'asisa
al pi hadavar asher yagidu lecha*.
So that's when he's directly dealing with the סנהדרין Sanhedrin, *Sanhedrin* of
seventy-one. It says, you know, they have the authority, ועשית על פי
הדבר אשר יגידו לך *asisa al pi hadavar asher yagidu lecha*, and
not him. So the דבר *davar* there is situated in his rejecting
the authority of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* of seventy-one, and that gets
you the seventy-one. So by making the link to his rejection of
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin. *Sanhedrin*, not to his being put to death, we're
linking it to the seventy-one and not to the twenty-three. He's put
to death with twenty-three, but he rejects the סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* of
seventy-one. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, but now that you've
got a זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* being, and but now that you've
got the נביא navi *navi* being seventy-one, ולהדר זקן ממרא ולגמר הזדה
הזדה מנביא *u'lehader zakein mamre ve'ligmar hazada hazada mi'navi*? Now let's go
and take the fact that if a נביא *navi* is judged with
seventy-one and we got that from linking it to a זקן ממרא
*zakein mamre*, let's just close the circle and get the זקן ממרא
*zakein mamre* to be judged by a בית דין *beis din* of
seventy-one, okay? דבר דבר
גמר הזדה הזדה לא גמר *davar davar gamir hazada hazada lo gamir*.
Nope, we only have a tradition of one link and not the
other. We link דבר דבר *davar davar* to go in one direction
to get from the idea that the נביא *navi* rejects, the זקן
ממרא *zakein mamre* rejects a בית דין *beis din* of seventy-one, so
the נביא *navi* is put to death with a בית דין *beis
din* of seventy-one, but we don't have the הזדה הזדה *hazada hazada*
link to get to say that the זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* is
judged by seventy-one. So it's very ironic. The זקן ממרא *zakein mamre*
rejects a בית דין *beis din* of seventy-one but he can be
judged by a בית דין *beis din* of twenty-three.
Maybe it's because he couldn't get a fair trial.
Oh that's interesting.
I mean it's already implied in the,
yeah you need somebody that's sort of outside of their authority. It's
also that the הלכה *halacha* of a זקן ממרא *zakein mamre* is
that he rejects the ruling of the בית דין *beis din* of
seventy-one and it says he goes back to his. city and continues
to rule as he had been ruling in the—before. So his—the sin
that ultimately seals his death warrant is when he's—when he's—when he's preaching,
you know, his—his ruling in his city. So he's judged by the
בית דין of his city, it would seem. Okay. Okay. לא זקן
גדול. Lo zakein gadol. Now, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol also needs—is—is only
with a בית דין of 71. מנא הני מילי, mna hanei milei?
what do you know this from? אמר רבי אדא בר אהבה Amar
Rabi Adda bar Ahava אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says, כל
הדבר הגדול יביאו אליך, kol hadavar hagadol yavi’u eleicha, דבריו של גדול,
devarav shel gadol, matters of a great person. Okay, מתיבי, meisevei, I'll
ask him this.
דבר גדול, davar gadol, דבר קשה, davar kashe, maybe the—we have a
ברייתא braisa that says דבר גדול davar gadol means a difficult matter,
which is probably פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. אתה אומר דבר
קשה או אינו אלא דבריו של גדול, atah omer davar kashe o
eino ela devarav shel gadol, no, maybe it means a matter that
relates to a, you know, a great personage. כשהוא אומר, keshu omer,
את הדבר הקשה יביאון אל משה, et hadavar hakashe yavi’un el Moshe,
no, 'cause in a later פסוק pasuk? when it repeats it, it
says that they followed יתרו Yisro's advice and the difficult matters they
brought to משה. Moshe. So it's showing you that that is a
synonym, it's a parallel for the words דבר גדול. davar gadol. הרי
דבר קשה אמור, harei davar kashe amur, so you see דבר גדול
davar gadol means a difficult matter. So it means difficult; it does
not mean matters of a great personage. Okay, so how do we—we
say here we learn it from this פסוק, pasuk if it's being
read by this ברייתא braisa as being just a difficult matter? הוא
דאמר כי האי תנא, hu d'amar ki hai tana, he says like
the following תנא, tana, דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא: braisa:
דבר גדול, davar gadol, דבריו של גדול, devarav shel gadol, a matter
of a great person. That goes to משה, Moshe, meaning, and משה
Moshe being 71. אתה אומר דבריו של גדול או אינו אלא דבר
הקשה, atah omer devarav shel gadol o eino ela davar hakashe, maybe
it means a difficult matter. No, כשהוא אומר הדבר הקשה, keshu omer
hadavar hakashe, הרי דבר קשה אמור. harei davar kashe amur. Exactly the
same פסוק. pasuk But here it's saying, if it wanted—later it says
דבר קשה, davar kashe, that means difficult. By using a different word
here in דבר גדול, davar gadol, it means the matter that relates
to a great person. הא מאי מקיים דבר גדול, ha mai mekayem
davar gadol, דבריו של גדול, devarav shel gadol, the matter that relates
to a great personage. והאי תנא תרי קראי למה לי, vehai tana
trei krai lamah li, so according to the one that says that
they both mean a difficult matter, why does one verse use the
word גדול gadol and one קשה kashe if it both means difficult?
חד בצוואה בעלמא וחד בעשייה. chad betzava’ah be’alma vechad be’asiyah. Nah, nothing
really interesting. One is where they were—he was, you know, he was
being instructed and the other is when he did it. Okay, but
it still doesn't answer the question why change the terms. ואידך אי
הכי לכתוב או גדול גדול או קשה קשה, ve’idach ee hachi lichtov
o gadol gadol o kashe kashe, don't change the terms. מאי גדול
ומאי קשה, mai gadol u'mai kashe, why does one use one term
and one use the other? שמע מינה תרתי, shma mina tartei, to
tell you that there are two concepts being communicated here. Difficult matters
go to משה, Moshe, and matters of the—of great personages go to
משה. Moshe. Okay, בעי רבי אליעזר, ba’i Rabi Eliezer, now, Michael, too
bad he left, 'cause here's a great question. When we say matters
of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or of a נשיא, Nasi, they
go to בית דין of 71, what matters? Matters that affect the
person of the נשיא, Nasi, like a capital crime? What about מלקות?
malkus? What about if his car—he had a car accident with somebody?
Would that go to a בית דין of 71? 'Cause you could
feel like maybe without that type of an authoritative בית דין, right,
you would not get a fair trial. Like any other בית דין
might be, you know, in—like, you know, sort of cowed by his
presence. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara starts by
the following question. So בעי רבי אליעזר, ba’i Rabi Eliezer, שורו של
כהן גדול בכמה? shoro shel Kohen Gadol bekama? Let's say a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol's ox gored. So we say מיתת הבעלים כמיתת השור.
misas habalim kemisas hashor. So בכמה? bekama? למיתת בעלים דידיה מדמינן ליה,
lemisas ba’alim didei medaminan leh, do we say the ox is killed
like the ox's particular owner would have been executed, so the ox
gets a 71
בית דין, או דילמא למיתת בעלים דעלמא מדמינן ליה? o dilma lemisas
ba’alim d’alma medaminan leh? No, no, no, just a normal execution, you
know, person would be executed, 23. So the ox gets 23.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מכדי מבעי ליה שורו, michdi mibaye leh shoro,
you're asking about the ox, מכלל דממונו פשיטא ליה, michlal demamono peshita
leh, it's obvious to you that a normal monetary case for even
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would go to a normal בית דין,
like a בית דין of three even. So the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא, peshita, of course, that's not about the person of the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, it's just about his property. So the גמרא Gemara.
says no, it's not so obvious. מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, הוה אמינא,
hava amina, I might have thought,
וכתיב כל הדבר הגדול, vechetiv kol hadavar hagadol, all matters of the
גדול, gadol, כל דבר שגדול, kol davar shegadol, anything, even monetary matters.
קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So it says not that way.
But of course, you could imagine that by the way, there's a
whole range of things between monetary matters and death penalty. What about
מלקות? malkus? What about קנס? knas? Right, what about minor
crimes, right, would those—what type of a בית דין would that be
for? So that's not really fully answered here, but at least the
question is being properly framed. Okay, let's just do a little bit
more. אין מוציאין. ein motzi’in. So now we go—now we're going to
do to
the—going out to war. This wasn't dealt with within the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi
Interesting that it wasn't dealt with within the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi. right? You
know, there's always these interesting things. Like why is there no
קדשים, Kodashim, ירושלמי קדשים? Yerushalmi Kodashim? רמב"ם Rambam says there was a
ירושלמי קדשים, Yerushalmi Kodashim, but we have no evidence of it. It
does not seem that there was a ירושלמי קדשים. Yerushalmi Kodashim. It
could be that certain things were a little too close to comfort,
you know, having lived in the aftermath of like an—attempted like, you
know, resurgence of Jewish sovereignty, you know, בר כוכבא, Bar Kochva, whatever,
the Hadrianic persecution and so on. Could be they did not want
to touch so much issues about thinking about קרבנות korbanos or thinking
about, you know, going out to war and kingship and so on.
So it's speculative, but it's interesting that the ירושלמי just jumped over
this question of מלחמת רשות, milchemet reshut, you know, and the בבלי
deals with it. So let's take a look. אין מוציאין, Ein motzin,
מנלן מילי? minlan milei? אמר רבי אבהו אמר קרא Amar Rabbi Abbahu
amar kra ולפני אלעזר הכהן יעמוד ve-lifnei Elazar ha-Kohen ya'amod וזה ביהושע
ve-zeh be-Yehoshua ושאלו במשפט האורים לפני השם ve-sha'alu be-mishpat ha-Urim lifnei Hashem
על פיו יצאו ועל פיו יבואו. al piv yetze'u ve-al piv yavo'u.
So that really sounds, you got Joshua's a מלך melech asking the
כהן kohen with asking the אורים ותומים. Urim ve-Tumim. It doesn't tell
you though the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin which is what we're talking about, it
tells you the other components. גמרא Gemara says: So, so יעמוד. ya'amod.
הוא, זה מלך. zeh melech. So he will stand, which is Joshua,
that represents the king. וכל בני ישראל אתו, ve-chol bnei Yisrael ito,
all בני ישראל bnei Yisrael with him. זה משוח מלחמה, zeh mashuach
milchama, which is interesting since when is the כהן kohen who's anointed
to go to war representing, you know, כל בני ישראל? kol bnei
Yisrael? It's not clear to me how they connect those dots. But
you also need a משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama to go to war.
וכל העדה ve-chol ha-edah and all of the community. So עדה edah
is a key word, you know, that means סנהדרין Sanhedrin for the
גמרא. זה סנהדרין. zeh Sanhedrin. So that tells you the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin,
You need the סנהדרין Sanhedrin? representing the people as well and you
need their authority. So you need God's authority, you need the משוח
מלחמה mashuach milchama to actually in the war itself being led by
the משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama and you need the סנהדרין Sanhedrin. like
which is I think both God's and the people's authority. ודילמא לסנהדרי
הוא דקאמר להו רחמנא דלישאלו באורים ותומים? ve-dilma le-Sanhedrei hu de-ka'amar lehu
Rachmana de-lish'alu be-Urim ve-Tumim? How do you know this is about going
to war? Maybe this is just in general saying that when you
want to ask the אורים ותומים, Urim ve-Tumim, either a מלך melech
can ask the אורים ותומים Urim ve-Tumim or the סנהדרין Sanhedrin? can
ask an אורים ותומים. Urim ve-Tumim. Maybe it's not just only specifically
about what you need to go to war, maybe it's about who
has a right to ask the אורים ותומים. Urim ve-Tumim. אלא fine,
we'll learn it from the following פסוק. pasuk דאמר רבי יצחק בר
ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא de-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Bizna amar Rabbi
Shimon Chasida כינור היה תלוי, kinor haya taluy, famous מדרש midrash from
ברכות, Berachot, right? דוד David had a... Now a כינור kinor is
a in modern Hebrew is what, a harp? Is it a harp
or it's a flute? רש''י Rashi makes it sound like it's a
wind instrument, like it's a flute. But we say כינור של דוד
kinor shel David is the harp, right?
Yeah, yeah,
in modern Hebrew it's a violin.
נבל nevel was a as a harp.
נבל nevel is a harp? Okay, רש''י Rashi makes it sound like
it's a wind instrument, but anyway, we'll say it's a harp.
היה תלוי למעלה ממיטתו של דוד, haya taluy le-mala mi-mitato shel David,
above his bed. כיון שהגיע חצות לילה, keivan she-higia chatzot layla, it
was midnight, רוח צפונית מנשבת בו, ruach tzafonit menasbevet bo, the southern
wind which... the northern wind which blows at midnight blew through the
windows, והיה מנגן מאליו ve-haya menagen me-elav and it would it was
his alarm bell, it would sort of start playing by itself. מיד
דוד עומד ועוסק בתורה, mi-yad David omed ve-osek ba-Torah, he would get
up and learn תורה. Torah. This is based on the פסוק pasuk
which is חצות לילה אקום chatzot layla akum by you know where
דוד David says I get up in the middle of the night
to praise you. So he would get up and he would learn
תורה Torah עד שעלה עמוד השחר ad she-ala amud ha-shachar until the
morning star. כיון שעלה עמוד השחר, keivan she-ala amud ha-shachar, day begins,
right? Crack of dawn. It's earlier than the crack of dawn. Business
starts. נכנסו חכמי ישראל אצלו. nichnasu chachmei Yisrael etzlo. The sages
came, אמרו לו: amru lo: אדונינו המלך, Adoneinu ha-Melech, עמך ישראל צריכים
לפרנסה, amcha Yisrael tzrichim le-farnasa, your people are poor, they need to
make a living. אמר להם: amar lahem: לכו והתפרנסו זה מזה. lechu
ve-hitparnesu zeh mi-zeh. Okay, go do business with one another. אמרו לו:
amru lo: אין הקומץ משביע את הארי, ein ha-kometz masbia et ha-ari,
the little handful of grain does not satisfy the lion, right? The
needs are too much, we don't have enough, you know, enough resources
to satisfy our needs. ואין הבור מתמלא מחולייתו. ve-ein ha-bor mitmale mi-chulyato.
A pit does not get filled with its חולייתו. chulyato. There's a
whole debate what that means. רש''י Rashi says it means if you
dig out dirt from a pit and you try to put it
back it won't fill in, but the opposite is true, because the
dirt is usually more loosely packed and you usually have dirt left
over. So תוספות Tosafos says it means maybe if you dig a
well to get water, the well doesn't fill with water, you know,
the water comes up but it doesn't get to the top of
the well. I also thought it meant that a well you could
say that a pit isn't filled from its hole, from the from
the emptiness of the hole, it doesn't fill the pit. Okay, but
the basic point is like, what do you mean do business? So,
you know, every nobody has enough money and everybody is trade trading
around their lack of sufficient money, so you know, it's like we
that does not actually provide for our needs. So he says, so
he says go invest in high tech. No, he said, so he
said: לכו פשטו ידיכם בגדוד. lechu pish'tu yedeichem bi-gdud. Okay, so let's
go to war. All right. מיד יעצו באחיתופל, mi-yad ya'atzu be-Achitofel, they
got advice from אחיתופל, Achitofel, who was the king's advisor, ונמלכין בסנהדרין,
ve-nimlachin be-Sanhedrin,
and also got the interesting what the difference between his יועץ yoetz
and נמלך. nimlach. Okay, but anyway maybe נמלך nimlach is more they
got the advice from אחיתופל Achitofel but they got the authority, they
got the license, the permission from the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin ושואלין באורים ותומים,
ve-sho'alin be-Urim ve-Tumim, they ask the אורים ותומים, Urim ve-Tumim, so they
got God's, you know, they got God's permission. אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, so now, that's all very nice, but still, that's just
a story. What's the basis for that? That you needed the סנהדרין?
Sanhedrin. מאי קרא? Mai kra? Where do you see this from the
פסוק? pasuk Because it says: ואחרי אחיתופל בניהו בן יהוידע, ve-acharei Achitofel
Benayahu ben Yehoyada, after אחיתופל Achitofel was בניהו בן יהוידע, Benayahu ben
Yehoyada, ואביתר ושר צבא למלך יואב, ve-Evyatar ve-sar tzava la-melech Yoav,
and then the king of the troops יואב. Yoav. So now we're
going to break all this up. אחיתופל זה יועץ, Achitofel zeh yoetz,
אחיתופל Achitofel was getting advice, the king goes to his advisor. ובניהו
בן
יהוידע זו סנהדרין uBnayahu ben Yehoyada zo Sanhedrin
so after you get from your advisor you go to the סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. How do you know that? So אביתר אלו אורים ותומים Evyatar
elu Urim veTumim and אביתר Evyatar is the אורים ותומים. Urim veTumim.
Where do you get that? So it says וכן הוא אומר ובניהו
בן יהוידע על הכרתי ועל הפלתי. vechen hu omer uBnayahu ben Yehoyada
al ha-Kereti ve’al ha-Peleti. So here in
another place you have ובניהו בן יהוידע uBnayahu ben Yehoyada juxtaposed to
כרתי Kereti and פלתי Peleti and כרתי Kereti and פלתי Peleti for
חז"ל Chazal means the אורים ותומים. Urim veTumim. So ולמה נקרא שמן
כרתי ופלתי? velamah nikra sheman Kereti uPeleti? כרתי שכרותין דבריהם Kereti she-kortin
divreihem
they cut their words like a divine utterance ופלתי שמופלאים מעשיהן uPeleti
she-mufla’im ma’aseihen
it’s wondrous how it does how the divine word emerges from it.
So if you have that juxtaposed so כרתי Kereti and פלתי Peleti
for them means אורים ותומים Urim veTumim so that maps onto אביתר
Evyatar and therefore who else would be asking from the אורים Urim
from תומים Tumim except the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin So now we’ve got the
advisor the סנהדרין Sanhedrin. and the אורים ותומים. Urim veTumim. ואחר כך
ve’acharei ken and then go to war שר צבא למלך יואב. sar
tzava lamelech Yoav. Fine. אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב אדא amar Rav
Yitzchak bereih de-Rav Adda ואמרי לה אמר רב יצחק בר אבדימי. ve’amrei
lah amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. מאי קרא? mai kraya? עורה כבודי?
urah kviudi? What’s the פסוק for the wind blowing and waking him
up? עורה כבודי עורה הנבל וכנור אעירה שחר urah kviudi urah hanevel
vechinor airah shachar
right? So the bestir you know the harp and the flute or
whatever and I will wake up the morning I will wake up
before the morning so that’s the harp waking up דוד. David. Okay.
ואין מוסיפין ve’ein mosifin let’s just do a little bit more here
you do not add to the city except with the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin,
מנא הני מילי? אמר רב שימי בר חייא amar Rav Shimi bar
Chiyya אמר קרא amar kra ככל אשר אני מראה אותך kechol asher
ani mareh otcha go straight to the פסוק by משה Moshe this
was a second דרשה in the ירושלמי. ככל אשר אני מראה אותך
את תבנית המשכן וכן תעשו לדורות הבאים kechol asher ani mareh otcha
et tavnit haMishkan vechen ta’asu ledorot haba’im
for future generations. It does not get into the details of מלך
melech and נביא and סנהדרין. Sanhedrin משה Moshe represents a סנהדרין Sanhedrin
and that’s what we’re focused on right now is the סנהדרין. מתיב
רבא. mative Rava. רבא Rava asks. כל הכלים שעשה משה משיחתן מקדשתן.
kol hakelim she-asah Moshe meshichatan mekadashtan.
All the vessels for the בית המקדש Beis haMikdash that משה Moshe
made the anointing with the שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah sanctified them. מכאן
ואילך mikan va’eilach if they wanted to make vessels after that עבודתן
מחנכתן. avodatan mechanchtan.
They were sanctified or they initiate through being put to use. ואמאי?
ve’amai? How can you do that? נאמר ne’emar וכן תעשו לדורות. vechen
ta’asu ledorot. If we’re going by this פסוק by the משכן Mishkan
you have to follow this procedure for future generations so the same
way משה Moshe had to anoint the vessels we should have to
do that for future generations לדורות הבאים. ledorot haba’im.
No. שאני התם דאמר קרא shani hatam de-amar kra וימשחם ויקדש אותם.
vayimshachem vayikadesh otam.
He sanctified them through anointing them. אותם otam במשיחה. bimshichah. They were
sanctified through being anointed ולא לדורות velo ledorot במשיחה bimshichah not for
generations. For generations it would be through putting them to use. The
גמרא says why do you read it that way? ואימא אותם במשיחה
לדורות אי במשיחה אי בעבודה? ve’eima otam bimshichah ledorot ei bimshichah ei
ba’avodah?
Maybe you have an option in future generations either to do it
the way it was done there or you have another option which
is to do it through putting it to use. שמע מינה. shema
mina. אמר רב פפא אמר קרא amar Rav Papa amar kra אשר
ישרתו בם בקודש. asher yeshartu bam bakodesh. הכתוב תלאם בשירות hakatuv tela’am
besheirut
because another פסוק says that they will be used in sanctity so
it seems to be signaling that the way in the future they
become sanctified is only through use. אלא אותם למה לי? ela otam
lamah li? So then if that says in the future it’s through
use why does אותם otam have to say that the original vessels
were only through משיחה? meshichah? אי לאו אותם הוה אמינא לדורות במשיחה
ובעבודה. ei lav otam havah amina ledorot bimshichah uva’avodah. I might have
said you needed both you know דהא כתיב וכן תעשו. deha ketiv
vechen ta’asu. It says you should do so I would have said
since the original vessels were anointing in the future you need anointing
and עבודה. כתב רחמנא אותם. ktav rachmana otam. אותם במשיחה ולא לדורות
במשיחה. otam bimshichah velo ledorot bimshichah. Fine.
So the original vessels were with anointing and later the vessels were
with use. Anyway the only reason we had this discussion which is
a little off topic is that if you’re going to use the
sanctification of the משכן Mishkan as the model for future generations you
have to discuss ways in which it is different.
Should we read one more? We’ll read one more. We’ll go to
8:45. Okay. ואין עושין סנהדריות. ve’ein osin Sanhedriyot. מנלן? mnalan? How do
you know that you need a שבעים ואחד shivim ve’echad בית דין
to make
the סנהדריות Sanhedriyot for cities? כדאשכחן במשה kedashkachan beMoshe דאוקי סנהדראות. de’uki
sanhedra’ot. משה Moshe made סנהדראות. Sanhedra’ot. Where did משה Moshe make סנהדראות?
Sanhedra’ot? So basically he followed יתרו's Yisro advice. So he made you
know he put he created all the other judges. So the appointment
of judges was done by משה. Moshe. So if the appointment of
judges was done by משה Moshe for the future the appointment of
all judges under the בית דין הגדול Beis Din haGadol would be
done by the שבעים ואחד. shivim ve’echad. ומשה במקום שבעים ואחד קאי.
uMoshe bimkom shivim ve’echad kai. Of course which leaves open the question
of who appointed those to sit on the סנהדרין גדולה? Sanhedrin Gedolah?
Right? The סנהדרין גדולה Sanhedrin Gedolah appoints all the lower judges but
who appointed the סנהדרין גדולה? Sanhedrin Gedolah? That never gets answered. Okay.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. מנין שמעמידין שופטים לישראל? minayin shema’amidin shoftim leYisrael?
How do you know in general that there's a מצוה mitzvah to
appoint judges throughout ישראל? תלמוד לומר שופטים תתן. talmud lomar shoftim titen.
שוטרים לישראל מנין? shotrim leYisrael minayin? How do you know you appoint
not just judges but like a police force? תלמוד לומר. talmud lomar.
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שופטים לשבטך. shoftim leshivtecha. Okay, שופטים לכל שבט
ושבט מנין? Shoftim lechol shevet veshevet minayin? How do you know it's
not just sort of federal level, but how do you know that
each tribe has to have its own, you know, judges, its own
סנהדרין, right because here we mean also specifically a סנהדרין that's over
the tribe? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שופטים לשבטך shoftim leshivtecha
because the פסוק says שופטים ושוטרים תתן לך בכל שעריך אשר ה'
אלקיך נותן לך לשבטך. shoftim veshotrim titein lecha bechol she'arecha asher Hashem
Elokecha notein lecha leshivtecha. Okay, so each tribe has to have a
בית דין that stands over it. שוטרים לכל שבט ושבט מנין? Shotrim
lechol shevet veshevet minayin? How do you know you gotta have a
state police force? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שוטרים לשבטך. shotrim leshivtecha. Now,
שופטים לכל עיר ועיר מנין? Shoftim lechol ir ve'ir minayin? How do
you know each city has its own local בית דין, his own
local סנהדרין of twenty-three? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שופטים ושוטרים תתן לך
בכל שעריך. shoftim veshotrim titein lecha bechol she'arecha. So שעריך, so every
gate, means every city. שוטרים לכל עיר ועיר מנין? Shotrim lechol ir
ve'ir minayin? How do you know you have your local police force?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שוטרים לשעריך. shotrim lish'arecha. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehudah omer אחד ממונה על כולן. echad memuneh al kullan. There's one
over all of them. Now this either for רש"י Rashi means there's
a סנהדרין גדולה Sanhedrin Gedolah that stands over the whole court system,
or תוספות Tosafot just says no, maybe it means there's a head
of each בית דין, שנאמר shenemar תתן לך. titein lecha. So somehow
there's one head. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer לשבטך ושפטו, leshivtecha veshaftu, מצוה בשבט לדון את שבטו, mitzvah beshevet
ladun es shivto, that let's make it clear, I mean it would
be implicit, but it means every tribe judges its own tribe. Each
state as it were handles its own affairs, and only very specific
national issues, you know, go to the סנהדרין גדולה Sanhedrin Gedolah of
seventy-one. Okay, so I think we'll end, we'll end with this for
now. And yeah, as I said...